<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator>
  
  
  <link href="https://website.asidiras.dev/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="https://website.asidiras.dev/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-07-02T08:52:14+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://website.asidiras.dev//</id>

  
    <title type="html">Alex’s Website</title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Hello, I'm Alex. I'm a Telecomunications student at the INSA de Lyon (France) and I love computer science too ! You will find articles about CS, Linux+GNU and other things I'm intrested into. I'll maybe write some daily life tips or things I use a lot etc.</subtitle>
  

  

  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Guide to a wholesome Python dev environment</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://website.asidiras.dev/2020/05/01/python-dev-environment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Guide to a wholesome Python dev environment" />
      
      <published>2020-05-01T17:41:35+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-01T17:41:35+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://website.asidiras.dev/2020/05/01/python-dev-environment</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://website.asidiras.dev/2020/05/01/python-dev-environment/">&lt;p&gt;I started coding with python, at the time I was 17 and barely knew about how much is the development environment important. Not just the computer itself is important but furthermore the Software. I was using windows and the basic Python IDE for an approx. 1000 lines project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Module import was a nightmare for me as much as learning the language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently faced a problem related to modules. My system’s Python version was 3.8 and I needed the 3.6 version for the script to run. Furthermore, I needed 3.6 version cryptodome module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some Qwant searches, later on, I found about Pipenv and Pyenv.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pyenv&quot;&gt;Pyenv&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pyenv allows us to have multiple python versions in one OS. By changing the symlinks and the Path variable it manages to change the direction of the Python commands and redirect to the other python versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a link to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pyenv/pyenv&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;, I may have done mistakes while explaining the process. Here are the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pyenv/pyenv/blob/master/COMMANDS.md&quot;&gt;main commands&lt;/a&gt; of Pyenv.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But What if we want to install modules alongside our newly created Python version?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well it’s “complicated”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had many problems and issues and that’s why I recommend the following tool :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pipenv&quot;&gt;Pipenv&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pipenv eases the problem of Python and Pip version Pyenv had. It creates a Pyenv environment with a Pip too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Said like this, Pipenv is the dream come true of Python developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It isn’t.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pipenv has sometimes problems with its pipenv.lock. I had a problem when managing the modules for my Deep Reinforcement Learning you can look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Ratatinator97/LunarLander-DQN&quot;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt;. The Pipenv install &quot;module&quot; command was taking an eternity and I seemed broken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here’s how I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://python-poetry.org/&quot;&gt;Poetry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;poetry&quot;&gt;Poetry&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Poetry’s website: &lt;em&gt;Python packaging and dependency management made easy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And trust me it is easy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t experience bugs about *.lock or colossal wait during a command. It is simple and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Poetry doesn’t change the Python version by itself, you have to create a Pyenv environment with the chosen version and then in the environment init a Poetry project. Look at their amazing documentation if you need some help.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">I started coding with python, at the time I was 17 and barely knew about how much is the development environment important. Not just the computer itself is important but furthermore the Software. I was using windows and the basic Python IDE for an approx. 1000 lines project.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Optimize your Linux experience</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://website.asidiras.dev/2020/05/01/my-linux-setup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Optimize your Linux experience" />
      
      <published>2020-05-01T17:41:35+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-01T17:41:35+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://website.asidiras.dev/2020/05/01/my-linux-setup</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://website.asidiras.dev/2020/05/01/my-linux-setup/">&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in Gnu+Linux you’re in the right place. I started using Linux as my daily drive 2 years ago. At the time I barely knew Linux. Here you’ll find my main tools that enable me to have a nice setup and be productive as hell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-shell&quot;&gt;The shell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is one of the &lt;strong&gt;main tools&lt;/strong&gt; if not the main tool of a Linux computer. You will spend a lot of time there and you have to be &lt;strong&gt;comfortable&lt;/strong&gt; in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the distros are shipped with &lt;strong&gt;Bash&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s a great and powerful tool but for me it wasn’t very enjoyable. Many times my &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tab&lt;/code&gt; completion did not work because of a typo. Other times it wasn’t handy when selecting items displayed by the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tab&lt;/code&gt; command. Bash’s tab auto-completion isn’t good enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I heard of Zsh, a &lt;strong&gt;child&lt;/strong&gt; of Bash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;zsh&quot;&gt;Zsh&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you had already learned Bash and started to be confident using it then don’t worry. Zsh and Bash are very &lt;strong&gt;similar&lt;/strong&gt;. Most commands are identical and the logic is the same. Although they seem identical, Zsh have some &lt;strong&gt;improvements&lt;/strong&gt; it’s father has not !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tab-auto-completion&quot;&gt;Tab Auto-completion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;is &lt;strong&gt;great&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://drive.google.com/uc?export=view&amp;amp;id=1NmzyZiOZzeVfV2D72WHs61li2tkaS888&quot; alt=&quot;A picture about the amazing features of Zsh&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;strong&gt;navigate&lt;/strong&gt; through the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tab&lt;/code&gt; results with your &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;arrow keys&lt;/code&gt; or just pressing &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tab&lt;/code&gt; to hop to the next element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A misspelled &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd documents&lt;/code&gt; will transform into &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cd Documents&lt;/code&gt; &lt;strong&gt;magically&lt;/strong&gt; !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;style&quot;&gt;Style&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zsh supports many &lt;strong&gt;theme&lt;/strong&gt;s. I don’t say Bash hasn’t but it’s good to know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;oh-my-zsh-&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ohmyz.sh/&quot;&gt;Oh my Zsh&lt;/a&gt; !&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is a &lt;strong&gt;great bundle of plugins&lt;/strong&gt; and themes ! It is an &lt;em&gt;incontournable&lt;/em&gt; of Zsh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t go through the plugins as they are already documented in their website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;be-carefull-you-have-to-use-the-zshrc-instead-of-the-bashrc-&quot;&gt;Be Carefull: you have to use the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.zshrc&lt;/code&gt; instead of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; .&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;battery-optimization&quot;&gt;Battery optimization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of students and developers out there use &lt;strong&gt;laptops&lt;/strong&gt; as main computers when it comes to &lt;strong&gt;work&lt;/strong&gt;. Most of our devices doesn’t last a day. I see a lot of colleagues that are plugged in more than &lt;u&gt;two times a day&lt;/u&gt; and they make me suffer because Linux has a &lt;strong&gt;lot&lt;/strong&gt; of battery optimization tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tlp&quot;&gt;TLP&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know what TLP stands for but I know it gives me more than &lt;strong&gt;2h&lt;/strong&gt; of &lt;strong&gt;battery&lt;/strong&gt; ! The install and setup is straightforward. Satisfaction guaranteed !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the link to the &lt;a href=&quot;[TLP - Optimize Linux Laptop Battery Life &amp;mdash; TLP 1.3.1 documentation](https://linrunner.de/tlp/index.html)&quot;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; !&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;powertop&quot;&gt;Powertop&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is another one battery optimizer. It gives me the same results that with TLP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;zram-zswap-or-zcache-&quot;&gt;Zram, Zswap or Zcache ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linux offers many solutions when it comes to optimize. You have seen two battery optimization tools. But what about &lt;strong&gt;Ram&lt;/strong&gt; optimization ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you define partitions for your Linux OS, you are often offered a Swap partition. Swap is a “fake” Ram, it acts like it but as it is stored in your hard drive it is &lt;strong&gt;much slower&lt;/strong&gt; than your Ram (physical). Yet not, don’t delete that partitions because Swap is very useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here we face multiple positions :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you &lt;strong&gt;don’t&lt;/strong&gt; have a Swap partition then go for Zram&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you have Swap go for Zswap&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you like risks and want bleeding edge tools go for Zcache, is it not ready yet but it does a better job than Zswap.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;If you want to know more about it, I recommend you to read &lt;a href=&quot;[kernel - zram vs zswap vs zcache Ultimate guide: when to use which one - Ask Ubuntu](https://askubuntu.com/questions/471912/zram-vs-zswap-vs-zcache-ultimate-guide-when-to-use-which-one)&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; on StackExchange.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gnome&quot;&gt;Gnome&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Ubuntu or the elementary OS you may know your DE (desktop env.) is   GNOME. I personally use Gnome under Wayland and I find it very good. It is the main alternative of Kde at this time and same you’re not fan of WM’s (Window Managers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gnome-vanilla-is-nice-but-can-be-improved&quot;&gt;Gnome vanilla is nice but can be improved&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t use Ubuntu then you may want to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://snapcraft.io/&quot;&gt;Snapcraft&lt;/a&gt; as well. It is a widely popular “App” Store. It is developed by Canonical so only Ubuntu based distributions support it in native. &lt;strong&gt;But other distros can use it too !&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you build your Linux from scratch you may want to have &lt;strong&gt;Flatpack&lt;/strong&gt; too. It is installed on Gnome by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that is very important is to be careful of the &lt;strong&gt;permissions&lt;/strong&gt; of the snap/flatpack package. They are usually &lt;strong&gt;very restricted&lt;/strong&gt; (i.e. can only use the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;~/&lt;/code&gt; by default). If you have a package that needs access to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/bin&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/usr&lt;/code&gt; you have to &lt;strong&gt;give&lt;/strong&gt; then the access to it. You can learn more about it &lt;a href=&quot;[Sandbox Permissions &amp;mdash; Flatpak documentation](https://docs.flatpak.org/en/latest/sandbox-permissions.html)&quot;&gt;there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unixporn&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;[r/unixporn - the home for *NIX customization!](https://www.reddit.com/r/unixporn/)&quot;&gt; UnixPorn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gnome isn’t as flexible as Wm’s or Kde when it comes to style. But it can &lt;strong&gt;change&lt;/strong&gt; a lot and improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the mains reasons to choose Linux over Windows or Mac is that you can and you may tailor your OS for your personal needs. You don’t use a “for everyone” OS. You have your own OS that is optimized for your workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For that you have to install &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gnome-tweak-tools&lt;/code&gt;. This module enables you to install extensions from &lt;a href=&quot;https://extensions.gnome.org/#&quot;&gt;GNOME Shell Extensions&lt;/a&gt;. It can be added with &lt;strong&gt;ease&lt;/strong&gt; from this website. If you want to change the style then. You’ll find &lt;strong&gt;extensions&lt;/strong&gt; such as Caffeine, Dash to Dock, User Themes etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend you use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gnome-look.org/browse/cat/134/order/latest/&quot;&gt;Gnome Shell Themes - Gnome-look.org&lt;/a&gt; as &lt;strong&gt;theme&lt;/strong&gt; store for Gnome. The themes are easily installable as you have a superb &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pling.com/p/1136805/&quot;&gt;helper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      

      

      

      
        <summary type="html">If you are interested in Gnu+Linux you’re in the right place. I started using Linux as my daily drive 2 years ago. At the time I barely knew Linux. Here you’ll find my main tools that enable me to have a nice setup and be productive as hell.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
</feed>
